so
[Music]
hello everyone this is actin flab live
stream number 40.2
on march 24th 2022
welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
this is a recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
hear about your qrf
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome we may actually have to change
this to all qrf are welcome
and we'll follow video etiquette for
live streams
check out
activeinference.org to learn more about
the activities in the lab
today in 40.2 we are continuing to learn
and discuss this awesome paper a free
energy principle for generic quantum
systems by
uh
fields fristen glazebrook and levin and
we're
really appreciative to have several of
the authors joining us today
and
in this
dot two we're just going to have
introductions and then jump right in to
several of the
notes that we left for ourselves from
last time
and
see where else it goes and anyone can
write a comment in the live chat and
we'll just
say hello again
pick up with some threads that were left
unspooled in the dot 1 and see where we
get in the dot 2 and how we continue
going forward
so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and i will pass it to dean
morning my name is dean i'm in calgary
in canada my emphasis i think is on the
practice part of active inference and
seeing how
it gets applied in in different contexts
and situations
i'll pass it to blue
i am blue knight i'm an independent
researcher in new mexico and i will
be facilitating the discussion today but
let me pass it off to oh steven if he's
still here stephen are you here
oh you're muted stephen
we still don't hear you
okay thanks stephen we'll continue on to
dave
dave i don't see also left okay okay
let's continue let's pass it down
to the authors we go so uh let's pass it
to mike first since you have audio this
time
yes i uh yep this is mike levin
um i do biology at tufts trying to uh
understand what uh what living systems
are doing at all scales and how uh
intelligence manifests in various um
unconventional uh embodiments across uh
who then and they compete in and
cooperate across scales to give us the
amazing phenomena we see in biology
awesome thank you
uh dave would you like to say hello
introduce yourself
maybe no audio also
okay how about
carl would you like to say hello
yes i would hello
i'm carl uh i'm one of the co-authors on
the paper i'm a neuroscientist from
london um i have to confess i'm a bit of
a passenger and admirer on this paper so
i'm here to learn as much to
as to answer questions so i'll pass it
on to chris who's
hi i'm chris fields i'm also an
independent researcher
uh working sort of on the boundaries
between physics and biology and
information science and
sort of convinced that those are all
three the same actual discipline
so
this is a paper that expands on that
theme a little bit
great thank you
so i think where we left off last time
was talking about how
the fep is asymptotically the principle
of unitarity and maybe chris would you
mind leading us off um here and if you
want to
point out a specific
maybe formalism or um place where we
should start i think it was the very
last formalism in the in the paper
actually
um but maybe if you would talk us
through that that would be super
appreciated
okay
um well let's let's talk first
informally
just about
the motivation for this idea and how it
might make sense intuitively
and again i'll go back to
carl's paper from 2019 a free energy
principle for a particular physics
which which the current paper is
obviously modeled after in a certain way
and
as we discussed last time i think
what
carl was able to show in particular
physics
was that the idea
of
the very intuitive idea of a thing
of something that
exists
and
um
importantly maintains its identity
as a single system
over time
and what that means is that it's it can
be measured by some other system
and
it can be measured repeatedly and
reliably
over time by some other system so so
thingness is associated with repeated
measurability
and what
carl was able to show in
in particular physics was that if we
assume that something is a thing
then we're effectively assuming that it
has a stable
non-equilibrium steady state density
and therefore we're assuming that it has
a markov blanket and therefore we can
treat it
as
implementing active inference
constantly predicting its own future
existence
and behaving so as to make that
prediction come true
to the extent that it can't
and
uh
such behavior may be
prevented or overcome by its environment
so the environment of something
may cause it to cease to exist
you know the thing could be a marble
sitting on a table
and its environment could include a
sledgehammer that's about to come down
on top of it
and and destroy its thinness
but as long as
the environment doesn't do that
uh
the the object can
continue
to uh
to execute active inference
and maintain its mark on blanket by so
do it
and of course it's markov blanket is
what defines it
as a separate entity as a thing
that's distinct from its environment
so let's translate all of that into
quantum theory
in quantum theory we have this
uh
notion of interaction as measurement
already
and we have a notion of interaction as
information exchange already
so
it's very natural to
take this whole picture and
and make the notion of measurement
over time precise in this
using this quantum theoretic formalism
and quantum theory also gives us a
a very natural implementation of a
markov blanket
which in physics is called a holographic
screen
and holographic screens were introduced
back in the
70s to talk about black holes
but a holographic screen
is is just a reformulation of the
concept of a markov blanket it's it's a
boundary that encodes information
and specifically
it's a boundary between two systems that
encodes all of the information that one
system can have about the other
so
it does
just what a mark on blanket does it
provides an information encoding
boundary
that gives
the systems on the two sides of it
identities for each other by
distinguishing them
and this notion of identity and quantum
theory corresponds to separability
inseparability just means lack of
entanglement
so if the joint
if you have a two
things
or a thing in its environment
then
if they're not entangled
you can talk about their states
independently if they are entangled then
you can't talk about their states
independently
and so the idea of thing this goes away
since thingness
uh implies having some sort of
conditionally independent state right a
nest density
that can actually be written down
so all of this fits together rather
nicely
and
so if we go back to
particular physics
of
the idea of
active inference
emerges
from that paper as a fundamental
underlying principle of physics
that
that tells us what we mean
by
think
or system
that's identifiable over time
so this is this becomes a very deep
principle
uh
deeper than newton's laws because
newton's laws actually talk about
objects that are identifiable over time
and
the
the the free energy principle and the
idea of active inference tells us what
we mean
when we talk about something being
identifiable over time
so if this is a if this is a fundamental
principle of physics then one would
expect
that would have some relationship to the
principle of unitarity
which is the most fundamental principle
of quantum theory and is typically axiom
one when one writes down the axioms of
quantum theory
uh
was was axiom one and von neumann's
origin back in the
thirties
uh or forties i can't remember which
so what's the principle of unitarian the
principle of unitarianity is just the
principle that in a closed system
information is conserved
so information is neither created or
destroyed in a closed system
so it's a fundamental conservation law
and it's exactly analogous to the
principle of conservation of energy
right the conservation of energy says in
a closed system energy is neither
created nor destroyed it's conserved
so the principle of unitarianity just
says this for information as well as
energy and we know that information and
energy are very closely linked
by by landauer's principle or by
boltzmann's
definition of entropy
or all of these other connections that
make physics informational
so
how does
the principle of active inference relate
to the principle of unitary what does it
say
about of
the conservation of information or what
does the conservation of information
tell us about the principle of the
principle of active entrance or the free
energy principle
well the first thing to know is that
unitarity applies to closed systems
so so thing environment pairs
and
active inference characterizes what the
thing is doing in response to its
environment
and of course it also characterizes what
the environment is doing in response to
the thing
uh and another benefit of quantum theory
is that it makes this symmetry between
any system and its environment how
manifest
makes it very explicit
uh but it's already explicit in the free
energy principle i mean the markov
blanket has two sides
and
the
the system
acting on its environment is the same as
the environment
sensing the system
and
in the same way that the environment
acting on the system
is the same as the system sensing its
environment
so interaction physical interaction is
information exchange in both frameworks
and and it's perfectly symmetrical
if the system remains identifiable over
time so does its environment
to exist its environment ceases to exist
because its environment is defined with
respect to it
that's why we call it its environment
um
so so all of these all of these
symmetries are built into both
frameworks
so um the free energy principle is
fundamentally about prediction
right vfe
variational free energy can be thought
of as prediction error or potential
prediction error
so
the free energy principle is about
the system being able to pre
the next state of its own markov blanket
oh and if it predicts the next state of
its own markov blanket
perfectly
then vfe is minimized to zero and that's
the asymptotic case perfect prediction
there's a question last time about
what's
asymptotic in the in the claim that
the free energy principle is
asymptotically the principle of
unitarity and the asymptotic
state as i think blue pointed out last
time is perfect prediction
so and now let's translate all this to
quantum theory and this is where the
figure in the paper that shows the disc
with the various triangles
uh comes into play i think that's figure
six but i've actually forgotten
uh
yeah it's it's that one
so
let's
now introduce this idea of a qrf which
is just a little package of predictive
capability
uh qrf means quantum reference frame as
we discussed
last time a reference frame is
implemented computation
that makes a measurement comparable
across time
so
a meter stick for example implements a
computation of length
and it allows us to compare
measurements of length across time
because we assume that it's fixed
and of course we can use a meter stick
because each of us has embedded in our
brains
a representation of length
in fact we have a representation of a 3d
coordinate system
without which meter states would be
useless
so we can use external reference frames
like meter sticks because we have
internal reference frames like our
representation of 3d space
and our intuitive understanding of
length
that we assume stays fixed over time and
that allows our measurements of length
to be comparable across time for us
so
now let's think about a qrf
um
as a way of of
as something that implements active
entrance or that enables a system to
implement active inference by allowing
it to compare its measurements over time
right prediction is meaningless
if you can't
compare your measurements over time
um
so and let's ask what what would it be
like
for a system to be able to perfectly
predict
the next state of its markov blanket
well the next state of its markov
blanket
is a state that its environment has
written by acting on it
so
our question of perfect prediction is
what would it be like for a system to be
able to perfectly predict the next
actions of its environment and notice
that the system isn't predicting the
next state of its environment it doesn't
know the state of its environment state
of its environments on the other side of
the marcon blanken what it's trying to
predict is an action of its environment
on it
which is the only action of its
environment that's relevant
uh and the only action of the
environments that's detectable
so
um its environment like it is
characterized by qrfs
right the situation is perfectly
symmetrical between the system and its
environment
um
so the question of produce
is its environment
and the system can predict its
environment's actions perfectly
only if it in the environment exactly
share
their qrfs
because the qrf
not only
interprets sensation it gives meaning to
action
so it says what your action is going to
be
so if i use my meter stick to cut a 2x4
my qrf the meter stick is guiding my
action it's giving it meaning it's
making it repeatable
in the same way that it makes my
perceptions repeatable and again that's
that's why we use these things we want
to be able to act in repeatable ways as
well as perceive in repeatable ways
and if we can't act in repeatable ways
then again the notion of prediction
becomes meaningless
so
perfect prediction corresponds to
perfect qrf alignment
so the question becomes now what does
perfect qrf alignment correspond to
and
um
jim glaisberg and another colleague
antonino marciano
who's a physicist
physicist in shanghai
showed in a previous paper
that perfect
perfect qrf alignment between a system
and its environment
is only possible if the system and
environment are entangled
so
perfect qrf alignment corresponds
actually to the collapse
of the markov blanket
because it corresponds to the collapse
of separability
which means that the ness is no longer
well defined
because it's no longer in a
conditionally independent state
and you can see that
if you think of what perfect qrf
alignment means
it means that
your actions correspond exactly
to my predictions
a
conditional statement
it's an exact same
so if i predict that you're going to do
x then you're going to do x period
which means that your state is no longer
independent of my state
your state actually depends on my state
and my state correspondingly actually
depends on your state
if you predict that i'm going to do x
then i will do x
that's what perfect prediction means
uh
when we translate it into this
qrf based concept
so perfect prediction and
of
the collapse of separability are the
same thing
so
the
asymptotic
limit of the fep which is perfect
prediction
corresponds to the collapse of
separability
well the collapse of separability is
just entanglement
and
the principle of unitarity
is the claim that any
isolated system
left to its own devices
uh will evolve its state which is the
joint state of any two of its components
will evolve toward
toward uh complete entanglement it'll
evolve toward a pure state in
in quantum theoretic jargon
so uh it's in this sense that the fep is
asymptotically the principle of
unitarian
it's that
it
its asymptotic condition is the same
as the condition that the principal
unitarity imposes on closed systems i.e
on
system environment
combinations
where
whenever i say environment i just mean
everything that exists that's not the
system of interest
so a system environment combination is
always a closed system by definition
so so that's my introduction and
we can start on discussion
that's great thank you stephen did you
have a question yes you can hear me okay
excellent i was just gonna ask that's
really helpful uh there's a lot in there
obviously
i was gonna ask in terms of
the pure unitarity would that be what
happens say at the
electron or the kind of
these normal quantum particle scales and
as you go
to scales above that you it becomes more
and more approximate you have less of
this uh
isotropic you know this this this
quality of knowing
and entanglement
um
well that's that's a very deep question
and it's a very good question uh let's
think about
the
the canonical entanglement experience
experiment the sort of bell epr
experiment
um
so i'll i'll draw it with my hands here
so in the canonical experiment
you've got a source
and it's located here in the in the
middle of my face
and it produces
an entangled pair of something photons
or electrons or bucky balls or whatever
you want
and they travel
apart
at the speed of light or something very
close to it
and at some point
they encounter two symmetrically placed
detectors and the detectors are operated
by observers who are always called alice
and bob
and
these detectors measure something and in
the canonical experiment they measure
spin
and
what
alice and bob
each observe independently
is a random
distribution of spins
and if we think of this as a
two-dimensional experiment
then
um
they they either measure spin up or spin
down in some coordinate systems so
alice and bob each pick a z-axis that
defines up and with respect to their
local z-axis they see a random
distribution of up and down
now
things get interesting
when alice and bob later get together
and compare their results
and what they find is that whenever
alice observes up
bob observes down and vice versa
and
so they conclude that their results are
classically correlated
but then it gets more interesting
because what we allow alice and bob to
do
is
constantly
alter
the direction that they
detect the spin in
with respect to their own local z-axis
so you can think of the spin detector as
like a polarization filter so like a
pair of sunglasses
and
what allison bob can do is
randomly and independently change the
tilt of their sunglasses
while they do this experiment
and in in real implementations of this
experiment it was first implemented
sorry
by
um
alan aspect in his lab in paris in the
early 1970s
um
and has since been repeated probably
hundreds of times by different groups
all over the world including the chinese
using a satellite to generate the
entangled pairs and measuring them
thousands of
a thousand or so kilometers apart
so if you remember the speed of lights
a foot per nanosecond so you've got a
lot of nanoseconds in there if you're a
thousand kilometers apart to play with
and
the so the the trick in this experiment
is that alice involved can change the
direction of their detector
within the time it takes for the
entangled pair to get from the source to
the detectors
so if it takes 10 nanoseconds
to get from the source to the detectors
they have to be able to change their
detectors within 10 nanoseconds
so that's why you want detectors that
are far apart
so
alice and bob redo the experiment
changing randomly changing the
directions that they're measuring
uh with respect to their local z-axis
and then they get together again to
compare their results
and what they find is
that
if alice observes up
bob will observe down
uh
even when they've been randomly and
independently changing
the directions of their detectors
so
one way to put that is
if alice decides to rotate her detector
45 degrees
then bob's result will automatically be
rotated 45 degrees
and it's symmetrical so vice and vice
versa so that's not classical
correlation
that's classical correlation that's
robust against manipulation
so
i was discussing this with carl a while
back
and i used this example
of if you and i are classic or
classically correlated then we may have
the same beliefs
about something so we might both believe
that the earth is round
that's classical correlation
now suppose someone convinces me that
the earth is flat
if
if that happens and you then believe
that the earth is flat that's
entanglement
that's classical correlation that's
robust against manipulation
so it's it's correlation no kidding
uh
correlation that that survives the
environment doing something to you
and
so
uh
now let's go back to this question is
this is this an effect
that only occurs in some microscopic
domain
and
the answer is it's an effect that was
first described by a theory that was
intended to only describe a microscopic
domain right quantum theory was
developed to deal with nuclear and
atomic and nuclear physics
and so there's this idea of the quantum
world which is very small
but the math of course applies across
the board
and
trying to think of quantum
theory trying to think of classical
physics as a limit
a mathematical limit of quantum theory
always runs into problems and the
problems are always the numbers go to
infinity that shouldn't be infinity
so
it's not
really accurate to think of
classical physics as some sort of
mathematical limit like h bar goes to
zero
of
quantum theory because if h bar goes to
zero lots of relevant energies go to
infinity
um
and this is this has been known for a
long time
nonetheless it's it's constantly taught
in this
classical limit
kind of framework that isn't really
correct
um so one
point of of
doing bell epr experiments at larger and
larger distances
is to demonstrate that quantum theory is
not really a microscopic theory
so
if you think of an entangled state an
entangled state is one object
it's not two electrons that happen to
have some mysterious relationship it's
one object that has one state
remember what entanglement means is
non-separability non-independence
across any decompositional boundary
so an entangled pair is one thing
and
what the chinese were able to
demonstrate
was you can have one quantum object
that's over a thousand kilometers long
now that's not microscopic that's big
uh
a nice way to think about entanglement
was introduced by leonard soskin
quite a few years ago
and raphael busso
with their idea that
an entangled pair is the same thing as
an einstein rosen bridge in spacetime
and an einstein rosen bridge is a black
hole and a white hole
connected end to end
or you can think of it that way it's
it's a
topological connection in space time
that simply identifies two points in
space time that would otherwise be
considered distinct
so this emphasizes that
if you have an entangled pair there's no
distance inside it
if you have two entangled electrons for
example that are a thousand kilometers
apart
as far as they're concerned they're
right next to each other
and in fact as far as they're concerned
they're located at exactly the same
point in space time
and that's what this er bridge notion
emphasizes to us
uh there's really no separation here
that the separation is an artifact of
our observational capabilities it's not
a characteristic of the entangled state
so entanglement actually calls into
question what the idea of distance even
means
uh it makes it it forces it to be
relative to us and that's that's that's
why there's all this discussion of
emergent space time in quantum gravity
and quantum cosmology
because if you think about things from a
straight quantitary point of view
space time isn't observable it's it's
just something it's
it's something that's relative to how an
observation is made it's not an
intrinsic property of anything it's not
antique as they say
so
let's go back to this question again
uh
if we think about
entanglement
and we think about observation
and we think about entanglement as
something that's observed by comparing
observations made by different observers
right neither alice nor bob in that
experiment can detect entanglement
they only realize that there's an
entangled state when they talk to each
other after they've done the experiment
then
this question of scale
becomes a question about how observers
interact
and what observers can know
about each other
and about each other's experimental
apparatus
so when i described the
the entanglement experiment
i said alice and bob each have their own
local z-axis
and when they get together and they
discuss their
results
and they compare their results
then they make a very important
assumption which is the assumption that
their z axes are comparable
so if during the experiment
bob's z-axis was varying at random with
respect to alice's z-axis
then
their results comparing their results
would be meaningless
because they'd be measured with respect
to completely different reference frames
so we have to make this assumption that
they have the same z axis
now interestingly enough
that assumption by itself
tells you that alice and bob have to be
entangled
or their z axes have to be entangled
so
um the idea of entanglement
kind of
expands
to
take in all aspects of the experimental
situation
as soon as one starts unearthing
these assumptions that we make
to
talk about comparability between
experiments
so
let's reel the tape back about half an
hour
and we see that the quantum reference
frames are what make experiments
comparable for
an observer
it's similarity or comparability of
quantum reference frames that make
comparing experiments possible for two
observers
but
if the two observers exactly share their
qrfs
in a way that's robust against
environmental manipulation then they're
entangled
so we've kind of come
full circle here
it's one
one can make this notion of entanglement
as macroscopic as one likes
and
again this is um
in a sense why why quantum gravity and
quantum cosmology are interesting
um it's what drives things like the
black hole information paradox which
you may have
read about
um
so so so we're now getting into
in a sense very fundamental physics how
how do we
uh
what's the relationship between
entanglement and the concept of
space-time what's the relationship
between quantum theory and general
relativity
um
which is you know the big the big
question in in physics from one point of
view
oh
but the short answer is you can make
entanglement
as big as you want
that's great thank you um that actually
leads into a question that i had back
way back when we were talking about
entanglement and quantum reference
frames
um so
i was just thinking like
if i cannot perfectly predict my own
behavior
is my quantum reference frame like
incompletely aligned with my own quantum
reference frame like i mean maybe we've
all had the experience of you know
predicting if i kick a ball in this way
i predict it'll go over there but like
it doesn't actually go over there so
like i mean we predict and we're off our
prediction is is not accurate so
is it like the actually a temporal
separation that that like makes that
happen or or what do you think happens
in those circumstances where my qrf
appears unaligned with my own qrf
now that's also that's also a beautiful
deep question
and
it it points to something that i think
can and should be stated as a general
theorem
which is
uh no system can perfectly predict can
perfectly predict its own state
uh
no system can observe its own state
its own total state
so
so that
situation is
ubiquitous and unavoidable
and
uh one could phrase it by saying
oh
a system can have a
a qrf or a meta processor as
one often uses that vocabulary
that represents itself so we all have a
self representation
that's in a sense metacognitive
we claim to know what we believe and
things like that
but of course those beliefs are all
one very coarse-grained uh two extremely
incomplete
of
three useful for making predictions but
they're often wrong
and
you know this is this is uh
this point this point has had huge
technological consequences i mean think
back to the history of artificial
intelligence
right in the
70s
uh
there was the the huge new
wave was expert systems
and
you know ai people redefined themselves
as knowledge engineers who were going to
go out and
interview experts and find out how
experts did things and coded up in
computers and soon we'd have
you know artificial expert systems that
did anything interesting
and
that
whole business failed utterly
right it was a complete disaster it
didn't work at all
why
well the simple explanation for why is
that experts can't tell you what they're
doing
expertise isn't verbalizable
and it's not just expert piano playing
is it verbalizable
you know expert systems engineering is
verbalizable expert computer programming
isn't verbalizing
uh
and that's that's just an illustration
of the fact that our meta processors
don't actually have a complete model of
the rest of us
much less a model of the rest of us plus
the metaprocessor
uh so it all it all comes back to this
general principle that a system can't
represent itself and so it can't predict
its own behavior
awesome
so between this work
actually i should ask carl to comment on
that tirade
because he's also thought about this an
extraordinary amount
well i'll certainly make the comment
that um that was marvellous you know
i'm glad this has been recorded because
this should certainly be transcribed and
i know it's probably
um implemented in the paper but it was
so beautifully articulated and clear
taking us through the issues i i really
enjoyed that um so i have loads of
comments but i won't i won't waste
people's time uh going through all of
them
that last issue is is um really
interesting about the meta processor or
the metacognitive aspects or a system
being able to measure itself i mean
there's a fundamental observation there
of course you know um you can't measure
yourself
the whole point of the
particular physics paper was to say that
you know yes there can be two kinds of
information geometries if you like
and the big move is that one system can
measure i.e infer
by possessing or having a movement on in
some sort of information geometry
infer
and belief update about something else
so at no point is there any room for it
they also start to infer about its own
inference
that that is
you know that's a mathematical
impossibility from from the random
dynamical system perspective i'm not
sure about the uh the quantum
perspective but it sounds as though
that's also true so that begs the
question and how on earth do we have the
illusion um that we know ourselves um
and of course you know
it's a little bit of a um a colloquial
question because you're 99.9 of things
don't actually think that they know
themselves so unless there's a
particular phenotype particle
or species
that boasts philosophers i'm pretty sure
that most of the things that exist
don't have any
any pretense to thinking that they know
themselves
it's a really interesting um point to
get across
anecdotally
you know i spend a lot of time
um taking people through examples
they'll probably go right back to things
like idea motor theory um
that you know the way that we
um the way that we develop a sense of
agency and think that we have a sense of
agency you know is a gift an illusion
that is probably unique to only a small
number of us and may not even be
available to people with say severe
autism
um
and
you know the example that i've literally
in the past day just written down in a
didactic way was that if you just take
um
vanilla active inference under a markov
blanket
and then
you
look at particular kinds of sparsity
structures where
the active states of the markov blanket
or the holographic screen
are hidden from the internal state so
these are special kinds of systems
i have a particular
sparsity where now the active states of
the markov blanket are now become hidden
from the internal states
and you can certainly license
some
entanglement
and i would um i'm gonna later ask about
the relationship between entanglement
and synchronization so i'll say
entanglement or synchronization
of the internal states such that the
internal states have beliefs about
the their action but those beliefs
become beliefs about action as a hidden
cause so there's absolutely no notion
from the inside that you cause that
you're just representing the cause so
the example i have in mind is you're
watching a little fish swimming around
looking for food gobbling up little bits
and particles of food and you think oh
that's a very sort of artful fish with
purpose and pragmatics and knows how to
navigate its world um
but from the point of view of the fish
all that is happening is that the water
and the particles are moving around it
in a benevolent
nurturing and fortuitous way such that
the water is
delivering food particles to the fish's
mouth so from the fish's point of view
it has absolutely no awareness that it
is the author or the agent that's
causing this synchronization with the
environment so
you know the the deeper question is how
on earth do we have the illusion that we
think we know our own our own agency and
how would and when do we develop agency
and you know
furthermore
it's not just agency about me it's
agency about other things at what point
do our uh in our say early neonatal
neurodevelopment
do we have these models of the world
that enable us to
distinguish between mother and self you
know and at what point do we
align our qrs if you like
with not mother but with the world
that enables us to now see mother as an
independent object uh so that is
something else that is an agent
and
you know the idea would then be well
perhaps if mother is nature perhaps i am
an asian and then you know
that i am now the author of my agency
and my actions but that is such a you
know that's such a high level thing i
imagine it only pertains to you know
to humans
that's what that's what i had said i'd
love to talk about um
the homologues of entanglement from the
point of view of classical
perhaps i've spoken enough at this point
um just a couple things uh came came to
my mind uh listening to this um what one
is that uh josh bongard had this uh
amazing uh paper and uh i think it was
about in 2006 or so where he had these
robots and these they were they started
out like a six-legged starfish but the
the cool thing about it was that they
didn't have an internal model of what
they were and or what their shape is or
how to move and they basically have to
flop around and make make models of uh
their own structure based on what
happened to them given various outputs
that they generated and eventually they
would build a model of what happens and
they would walk around and so on and two
interesting things followed one is that
you could unlike traditional robotics
you could rip off one of the legs and
they would very soon revise the model
and keep going in different ways so they
weren't tied to that particular self
model right they would have to discover
it from scratch but it was still sort of
plastic throughout their whole lifetime
and they could they could get along so
they had that plasticity and the other
thing is that and um chris christophe
adami wrote a nice uh kind of uh
interpretation piece of this he he
described they they spent lots of um
lots of time being completely inactive
and basically running through uh
quote-unquote mentally running through
all the different things that they could
do and what they think was going to
happen uh before they actually moved and
so you go
chris uh call that uh dreaming you know
that they would basically sort of play
out uh before you know in between their
actual motions where they would go
around testing it they would actually
sort of play this out internally and try
to refine the model such that then when
they do move they would actually make
movements that uh maximally sort of
distinguish the different different
possible models and so on anything you
know you said that you can watch them
dreaming about about their shape um so
and then the other thing i just wanted
to briefly mention this this idea of uh
when and how do you recognize that
you're an agent and that actually you
need to act for things to happen versus
just having the environment do things
too i suspect that one of the things
that drives it very early on is this is
this notion of stress and i don't have a
particular
uh
i don't have a theory of why stress
feels stressful but but just on a purely
functional level i think that what
happens in in cells you know so so very
early long before you get to humans or
anything like that i think that what you
get is this um
this is a set of mechanisms that that
evolved from things like uh stress about
protein folding and so on but then then
basically scaled up to be stress about
metabolics and stress about morphology
and stress about behavioral issues and
and so on that basically is a is a
system-wide metric of um
the delta between what's going on and
what you'd like to have going on right
the delta between your set point and
then what's happening now and what then
i think that drives a strengthening of
this uh of of the agency model because
what will happen is as you as you as you
slowly learn that you can do things that
reduce the stress level it kind of
solidifies this idea that it's actually
at least some amount of it is up to you
to make life better and and so you then
then act and of course we know that
breaks down and sort of learn
helplessness assays and so on that's
that's that that really is is very
traumatic for for all kinds of creatures
well be long human
can i can i speak to that because
there's some great points there please
yeah um so three really important uh
things being brought to the table there
um
so
i'm bound to forget the third one if i
start the first one i just want to so
i'm coming back to blue's um
question about sort of a um qrs and
alignment and that and
you know one obvious sounds that um what
could bring to the table is that
learning is the alignment of the qrs so
learning at all scales you know and
we're talking here about developmental
skills for example we're talking about
robots that learn to repair themselves
or learn their new qrfs and if we remove
a limb or a child
learning to
make sense of its world
then um you can look at the slow process
of alignment of the qrs the things that
are invariant over the faster time
scales of at which there is
classification exchange on or in
the holographic
screen as simply
a um movement from a state of um
disentanglement to a state of
entanglement um as you become better and
better at predicting but to become
better at predicting you have to align
your qrs you have to
to align that um i think the sort of the
robot example is a perfect uh a nice
illustration of that
in the sense that these robots were
equipped
with um the ability to learn about
themselves and of course the you know
the analog um in developmental
psychology and indeed i would imagine
developmental neurobotics
um is motor babbling it's basically you
know
soliciting
um
outcomes
sensory outcomes in order to start to
disambiguate between what did i call
that or did you cause that you know what
parts are apparently under my control
but of course you know that's a very
anthropomorphic interpretation there's
no minus or minus implicit but certainly
the learning of the world models and the
body models um is probably the first
thing that any artifact has to contend
with because you see that in children
you're shaking their rattle to to
[Music]
solicit and
actively solicit
the conjunction of visual motion
um proprioceptive feedback from the
muscles causing the movement of the
mobile or the rattle and the auditory so
soliciting uh conjunctions or
correlations that are explainable and
predictable
in multiple modalities
so you may then ask why on earth what is
the imperative for that kind of behavior
what drives action
to solicit this um opportunity to
learn
the
the correlations and the coincidences
and the conjunctions um and that brings
us to the second point um
[Music]
these robots
dreaming tell you immediately that at
some level
they have an internal model
of the consequences of action
and that tells you immediately that
you've got
if you wanted to write that down from
the point of view of classical active
inference you've got a
um
a belief
structure
on the inside
that covers both
the
covers both the external world
and these hidden actions and the actions
upon the of the world and the
consequences of those actions on the
external states that's a very
sophisticated generative model to have
and you're getting now into the world of
planning as inference so a thermostat
won't work doesn't have that and yet
these robots do have them so it tells
you that there are two natural kinds of
particles that mark off blankets
[Music]
um at least two kinds of one of which is
more like a thermostat and one of which
is more like um
a sort of um i was thinking sort of like
an ashby um
homeostat or alistar but certainly more
like these sort of uh robots that can
learn about about themselves and the cue
and the
crucial distinction i think is that the
agent has now started to represent the
consequences of its actions but without
realizing it's its own actions we still
haven't got to the level of the other
metacognitive i am aware kind of kind of
artifact
and interesting it comes back to
what i was saying before about natural
kinds where one's active states are
hidden from the internal state so they
have to become inferred
you have to infer them they don't
they're not they are opaque to the
internal states and as soon as you say
it like that then you're naturally
talking about systems that um
can effectively uh
engage in planning as imprints so they
have to have plans in their heads
uh in order to act which you know
corresponds to
to this dreaming um from the point of
view of the
uh the
active inference
um then you ask what are the objective
functions
um or what are the principles of least
action that would
um
apply
to these kinds of plans and when you
work it through
then one important component of
the
sort of the pathogens or the actions in
question
is
a drive to resolve uncertainty
so we come back to this notion of the
child soliciting proprioceptive
extraceptive
[Music]
sensations that enable it to resolve
uncertainty and this is exactly the same
principle behind the optimal bayesian
design that we design experiments
that are going to resolve the
uncertainty to the greatest extent
possible under our current internal
models or hypotheses about how the world
works
and that brings me to the third great
point
about stress
and
the
the really important
place of stress and uncertainty and
angst and not knowing what to do next or
not knowing what's going to work
in driving behavior because if a large
chunk of the imperatives
or
planned action
is to maximize information gain
or
minimize expected surprisal or reduce
uncertainty then you can see easily now
why it is situations of uncertainty and
stress that will necessarily
cause the most
epistemic
responses in order to drive the system
or the the
in this instance the agent
to resolve that uncertainty
the final point now and this is
basically paraphrasing what mike just
said
if the system sees itself
behaving more
in times of greater uncertainty it may
now learn that
and and now have the idea oh i am the
kind of system
or i am behaving as if i am the kind of
system that responds more when under
stress
and then you'll become aware of that and
then you can get into the psychiatric or
psychological aspects of stress you may
not if you're just a pro gene you may
just show a sort of um
sort of selection for selectability like
response um but there's you know the i
think that you know the two fundamental
mechanisms the imperatives that are
being fulfilled here in accord with
basic conservation laws or principles of
least action from the classical
perspective um are account for exactly
the same kind of behavior i think the
interesting thing about stress and
surgery though is that we're not talking
about
um
the um the content of implicit belief
structures but the the the second order
statistics the uncertainty
and that's i think you know brings a
whole level of analysis to the table
because once you talk about uncertainty
and representations of uncertainty
um in say internal states
um
then from a psychological perspective
you can start to talk about tension and
consciousness um from the point of view
of an engineer we're talking about
things like calm and gain and get
getting the estimates of noise levels if
you like uh correct um
and
i'm not sure what
what
where
the if you like the well
let me ask um from a quantum theoretic
point of view
is uncertainty baked internet can you
can you have a stressed quantum
quantum formulation
i'll put that out there well stop
talking now
yeah just uh just to answer that
question
uh
if if when if one
thinks about quantum theory
of
from with a bayesian view of probability
right with a
kind of subjectivist notion of
probability
um
which
i mean that
point of view was really pioneered by
chris fuchs and and now david merman for
example has taken it up and
written some very good things about it
um
then this notion of uncertainty
reduction
of
becomes the explanation for why you do
experiments and build theories and and
it all becomes very well aligned i think
with with
the idea of active inference and in fact
we
wrote into that paper at the very end
some remark about
uh
this cubist perspective about quantum
theory becoming a result not an
interpretation
when we think of of
quantum theory is in a sense a way of
reformulating the idea of active
inference
out
so i think they're very consistent
right
uh
a stressed a stressed quantum is
stress quantum system is just a system
that gets
uh observational outcomes that it
doesn't expect
so you know we
we have to think of
such systems as
having generative models
and thinking about
the generative model of an electron
uh is a bit of a stretch
right because
the electron
is only characterized by mass charge and
angular momentum
so
it can't really
have
expectations about much right an
electron can have no expectations about
the external electric field for example
it can detect that it can respond to it
but it can't predict it
and
if we think about
something like an electron
then
we can focus in on this idea that having
a generative model
requires having enough memory
to
keep a record of the most recent
observation at least the most recent one
and if you want to have a good
generative model then you better have
enough memory to keep a record of quite
a number of observations
and
it's this memory resource
that really simple things like electrons
don't have
so
uh
they're they're not great
predictors
um
because they don't have the memory to
allow
being a great predictor
and as as both
carl and mike were saying
um
in a sense you you have to have memory
to be able to feel stress
you have to know that your predictions
were wrong so you have to remember what
your predictions were
so memory becomes a really key component
of the theory
how
once you put it into this
language
because the language in a sense forces
you to
to lay out assumptions about what the
what the computational resources that
are being
required are
that wasn't very coherent but anyway i i
just wanted to stress the role of memory
here
perfect thank you carl
yeah just to reinforce and endorse that
last point um and uh just tell exactly
the same story in a much more pragmatic
way the point of view a statistician so
i heard chris say that basically
that if i want to go beyond being a
little electron or a thermostat and i
want to now um infer the quality of how
noisy are my sensors for example my
thermo sensors if i'm a thermostat that
will require me becoming a little
statistician and what does that mean
well basically i'm going to be
estimating the standard error or the um
the experimental variance there's
something quite important about that you
know which which
comes back exactly to the computational
resources and memory if you do a simple
t-test as a statistician on some
experimental data you necessarily have
to acquire lots of data points and store
them
and of course that is just the degrees
of freedom associated with your t-test
or your f-test so the degrees of freedom
score the number of data points that
you'll be able to remember and you need
a sufficient number in order to get a
precise estimate of the uncertainty so
literally the degrees of freedom in
classical statistics is literally
a statistic that scores your confidence
in the estimation of the standard error
which is pooled over
multiple observations
which is an attempt to estimate on
average if i observe with this kind of
or i
i asked my questions or i wrote to my
holographic screen and i or i um
solicited these sensory states um you
know
what would
on average what would the uncertainty be
associated with it so i think it's a
really important point about the
computational resources the degrees of
freedom literally in the sense of the
degrees of freedom associated with your
f test all the degrees of freedom you
have available for the computing power
to actually get up to these second order
inference machines or takes on on second
order inference so and i think that is
particularly important when it comes
back to mike's observation about stress
and uncertainty and these higher order
ways of making sense in the world but in
this instance making a sense of
sensations that are accrued over time
not about the content but about the
reliability of the or the precision of
that content so this is a really
important point
awesome
so that kind of oh chris go ahead
if i could just pick up on this and and
take it in yet another highly related
direction
it's just to point out that that all of
these resources are energetically
expensive
so if i'm going to devote
space in in my state space to recording
memories
then
that's only useful if i can defend those
memories against entropy
if i can keep them from decaying
so i've got to consume energy to write
the memories i've got to consume
energies to energy to maintain the
memories
and then i have to consume energy to
read the memories
and consume energy
to compare
what i've read with what i see with my
kind of current event sensors
so
as we start adding these computational
resources to systems the energy budget
goes way up
and
uh it's it's another
kind of
thing to keep in mind as we think about
these in terms of embodied forms whether
they're robots or organisms
that
these these entities are extracting
this free energy that they have to have
to run their computations and maintain
their memories and all that from the
environment
so here's this is another input that in
a sense is not sensory
but it's still having to flow through
the markov blanket and still having to
flow through the boundary between the
system and its environment
and
a lot of the systems actions on its
environment
it's expenditures of of um of its own
internal energy
are to acquire this free energy
so you know we
we go out and
shop for groceries make breakfast or
whatever
uh that's stuff that we have to do to
keep all these
processes running
so it ties metabolism and cognition
together in a way that they aren't often
tied but that they have to be to make
sense of what's going on
great
so just on that point um something that
we had
written down as a question from last
time
and in terms of
an electron having a generative model
and discussing agency we had talked
about free choice and it was brought up
in the paper
several times both in terms of like any
physical system having free choice if if
one physical system has free choice they
all have free choice they generate like
their their um noise generating things
like free choice generates noise in both
classical and quantum systems and so i
just was wondering if
you could maybe say a few words about
the difference in free choice
in an electron and the difference in
between between an electron ends like a
human or an animal or even a cell
what is that difference and is that also
related to memory
uh
is that a question for me
a general question
for anyone
well i'll make a couple of comments
uh
one is
remember in talking about the canonical
entanglement experiment
um
part of the description is that alice
and bob can
alter
the directions of their detectors
however they want to at random
independently
whatever you want to call it
during the experiment so that's the free
choice assumption or that's called in
physics the free choice assumption
and
what that assumption means
it's effectively an assumption of
independence
it means
that there's not some common cause in
the past
that determines what they're going to do
as they operate their detectors
and one can reformulate
quantum theory
of in terms of what's called super
determinism
and super determinism
is the idea that
there is some common cause in the past
that
determines
how experimenters are going to do their
experiments
and in particular determines how alice
and bob are going to rotate their
detectors in this epr experiment
and
super determinism is kind of the
ultimate non-local hidden variable
wow
so
it
it allows you to predict exactly what
entangled pairs are going to do and in
fact it renders entanglement a classical
effect
right it just says these these
kind of super classical correlations
are present
because there
there was no independence to begin with
everything was determined from the very
beginning
and if you think about
as as mentioned last time newtonian
physics is formulated by laplace
it's a super determinant deterministic
system
so anything that happens anywhere in the
universe
instantly affects what's going on
everywhere else in the universe
and the most the most
current formulation of that is bromine
quantum mechanics where the motion of
any particle
depends instantaneously on the motion of
every other particle in the universe
and that's how newtonian gravity worked
right before einstein imposed locality
by making the speed of light finite
so all of these things are
interconnected assumptions about space
time assumptions about the speed of
communication assumptions about super
determinism
and assumptions about
free choice
it's
that cluster of assumptions
that the so-called free will theorem in
physics is about or theorems there are
now a couple of them
due to conway and cocon
and
what those theorems show is that
from a formal perspective
in physics if you assume that some
system has free choice so if you assume
that some system
is not subject to super determinism
then you have to assume that all systems
have free choice in the sense that all
systems are not subject to super
determinism so you can't limit super
determinism to some little piece of the
universe
and say it only applies here uh it
doesn't apply anywhere else
and in particular it doesn't apply to me
i have free choice even though nothing
else does
that's mathematically inconsistent
so that's that's
what what the free choice assumption
means is in a strict
physical context
thank you very
cool new zealand do you have a question
i was just going to ask a little bit
more about the um the degrees of
entanglement and
whether that's
different in terms of the observers
degrees and
versus the like
the mechanical nature of quantum
mechanics degrees
um
i think you've answered that to some
extent but
just just the way that that
varying degrees of entanglement can be
thought about and whether that maybe
ties into how the hilbert space
is is thought about at the same time
yeah this this assumption
or this question touches on uh why we do
everything in the paper from the point
of view of a bipartite decomposition
so we always we always decompose into a
system in its environment in the paper
um
and
there are two reasons for that
one is to keep it simple
and the other ones to enforce the more
called blanket condition
so
it's
entirely commonplace
to do physics in an open systems
framework
where we talk about
um
two systems we can call them alice and
bob again
that are embedded in a common
environment
and
in that case whenever you have
a tripartite or greater
some sort of multi-particle kind of
decomposition of the state space
you can talk about degrees of
entanglement
uh between different systems
and you can you know
cut up the state space any way you want
to and ask about the entanglement
entropy of some component of it
um
and you and you get these ideas of
partial
or they call it non-monogamous
entanglement
um
and that's all well and good it's it's
mathematically complicated it's
conceptually complicated
but in in a sense it deeply violates the
markov blanket condition
because in point of fact each of us is
an observer
and
our goal is to
to say what does the world look like to
an observer
and from alice's point of view
of
bob
is a decomposition of her markov blanket
right
alice has to
actively disambiguate
of
her incoming signals
into signals that she attributes to bob
as an entity
and signals that she attributes to the
rest of the environment as an entity
so that's an active cognitive process on
alice's part
uh that's what the markov blanket
condition
that's halamar called blanket condition
in a sense forces us to think
so
the marco blanket condition itself
makes us take this idea of bi heart
decomposition seriously
and
again you can think of this
in terms of of implicit assumptions
about resources
if you think in open systems terms and
so you think of alice and bob as
as
antic entities that are that are
separate from each other
by a priori assumption
and separate from their environments by
operatory assumption
then you systematically underestimate
the amount of cognition that alice and
bob have to be doing
and so you systematically underestimate
their energy consumption
their
their uncontrolled
effect on the environment i.e generation
of waste heat
acquisition of free energy resources and
all that
so
it's not just a
philosophical difference
it's
a difference that leads you to make
genuinely alternate predictions about
things like metabolic load
so
that's why we
do things in this bipartite framework to
respect the mark on blanket condition
and to
keep our assumptions
about energy flow explicit
can we
take that to the latter sections in the
paper about biological cognition
what are the implications for this for
biological systems
yeah carl
well
um just to pursue that sort of thought
experiment where you're trying to now
say you wanted to use active inference
to stimulate alice and bob observing a
pair of electrons and remembering that
the pair of electrons are one thing so
you've now got a tripartite
with three markov blankets in play
um and many of the issues for example um
the super determinism that allows some
assumptions about the
qrf alignments between bob and alice
to be in play
and also
the discussion of
how
um
alice has to have uh has to
contextualize
sensations from bob
and under a belief or an internal model
that bob is indeed another markov
blanket and possibly a markov blanket
very much like alice
what you are saying is that two of these
particles bob and alice have aligned qrs
that could have been aligned
historically uh under the super which i
never heard of before but i like the
word apple super determinism um and that
may be a prerequisite to understand the
experiments that we were taking through
uh previously when looking at the third
markov blanket which would be the uh the
electron um
uh or the two electrons but for
simplicity um so um that from a
biological perspective tells you
something quite um
uh quite interesting in the sense that
um it starts to get to
um
the
if it's the case that you can basically
carve up a bunch of states not in a
bipartite way but in a multipartite way
and that carving is by inserting
markov blankets
[Music]
to define the partition
under every um if you like subset of
that space
now becomes internal to its own markov
blanket so there are now no external
states all we have in play now
are a set of internal states each
equipped with a holographic screen or
markov blanket states they're exchanging
with other internal states then there's
some really interesting questions about
how that system will evolve um you know
from the point of view of the discussion
we've been having
it's going to evolve and under the
principle of unitarity to entanglement
so it's going to from the from a
classical perspective
um if you allow me it's going to tend to
a a state of um
generalized synchronization where
everything collapses onto the same
synchronization manifold and everything
is indistinguishable there's perfect
mutual predictability there's a
communication of an elemental and
fundamental sort so everything has
basically in everything is singing from
exactly the same hymn sheet that's the
natural way of things the free energy
principle is just one way of describing
that natural tendency
what would that look like cognitively
well it would look as if the markov
blankets were trying to learn about each
other and to the extent that they can
act on each other they're going to
try and solicit
um the kinds of outcomes that would
enable them to learn about each other so
we're now going to get a situation that
is driven by the imperative towards
mutual predictability and entanglement
um that's an illusion
you know all that is actually happening
is that the system is becoming entangled
but it will look as if
all of these separate um
markov blankets or um
sets of internal states are aligning
in a mutually compatible way they're qrs
so they can exchange and predict each
other and if there's if you like an odd
man out namely the pair of electrons um
then you know then there will be an
asymmetry and there will be graded
degrees of entanglement um you know for
multiple levels for example um if
they're both observing a thermostat then
the thermostat's not going to be very
good at learning how to align it's qrs
with bob and alice but you know they're
all going to make the best job of it
ultimately of course with good cultural
economic construction they'll they'll
build better thermostats and become
little robots and then they can all live
happily and communicate so i think that
sort of the cognitive
thing here
comes again back to
learning to live in your world
as an apparent expression
of the
the
inevitable progression to entanglement
whereby we try to learn about each other
under the plausible hypothesis that you
are like me it's not necessarily true
but it you know it's one hypothesis you
can bring to the table you never know
when it's true or not
but that's certainly one hypothesis that
would work very nicely for alice and bob
if they can develop a common language so
this notion of aligning qrfs between two
blanketed systems
particles
that are sufficiently similar
then just simply translates into
learning uh to share the same narrative
to share the same language
in order to render
everything mutually predictable so i
know exactly what you're going to say
next and you know exactly what i'm going
to say next and we come now to this
asymptotic limit of zero prediction
error zero free energy and complete
entanglement and that would be the your
the object would have no ukraines or
brexits or or anything if we can get
there
but that would be the other direction of
travel from a biological perspective
just just to that there are simulations
of this from a purely classical
perspective
um and what you'd normally do
is start off with um
two
systems um
that
think they have um strange attractors
usually a lorentz attractor
so they think that their dynamics um
are
generated by their act their autonomous
or their active states um creates stuff
out there that um has
a chaotic aspect and i i i say that
explicitly just because this sort of the
notion of free will and choice in the
classical domain usually reduces to
sensitivity to initial conditions which
strikes me as a homolog of the super
determinism game
can you go right back to the beginning
and
explain everything um
and in sort of classical dynamical
systems there are certain situations
where you can't because you get a
sensitivity to initial conditions um so
that would leave space or uh free will
and choice at certainly
you know at one level but sorry i
digress
so what you do is you basically put sort
of two chaotic systems with sensitivity
to initial conditions together
but they're not identical in the first
instance but if they can exchange
sensory inactive states or they can
exchange across a shared holographic
screen
so now back to the bipartite situation
then they will naturally in fact if you
think about they can't do anything else
um they will naturally
come to a state of entanglement i.e in
if um
generalized synchrony and if you allow
the parameters of the equations of
motion that underwrite these chaotic
dynamic dynamics to also maximize mutual
predictability or minimize free energy
then they will actually come to show an
identical synchronization because they
will learn to become like each other
just like mike's robots
but in this instance they're learning
about the other person simply to make
things predictable so then you will have
a shared narrative and in principle um
you should be able to
a kind
i i mentioned that because i know chris
wanted to talk about language we wanted
to talk about you know
quantum physics is just basically a
description of of communication and
language uh i don't think we're gonna
have time to do that but i thought i'd
slip that in anyway
[Music]
chris did you want to say a few words
quantum and language
uh well that that was that was lovely
carl when i i i
like the idea of this kind of
uh
simulation leading to to generalize
synchrony
i think it's interesting from this
perspective that
we
uh
we always divide
our environment into
entities like us
and then at least one entity that's
radically unlike us
which we call the shared environment or
the the open environment for the general
environment or something like that
and um
so we have this sense of a
a social grouping of similar entities
uh
that are commonly exposed to this vastly
dissimilar entity
with which we don't share a common
language
and we're not very good at predicting
and so on
and so we always have this kind of
open systems point of view
and
uh
one of the functions of
this
vastly different system with which we
don't share a common language is it's
our free energy source and sink
so it's where we put our waste heat
and it's it's where we get our free
energy for doing computation
um so i
i think it's interesting to think of
this situation of
uh kind of local
synchrony or local entanglement or a
local language community
local shared predictability
embedded in
this unpredictable
chaotic
and in a sense
in principle chaotic because it's
the waste heat dump
right
now
we've assumed a priority that we can't
understand it because it's where we're
putting
uh all of our
the thermodynamic
entropy that we're creating
uh
we
we put ourselves in a
conceptual bind almost automatically by
being systems that that have to generate
this entropy and put it somewhere
so i like this this classical to quantum
correspondence very much and i i think
it works very nicely
awesome
mike
yeah um i want to i want to float an
idea which is literally just a few days
old so it may be a complete nonsense but
i'll float it anyway because i think
it's uh
i think it's it's it's relevant and i've
been thinking about it this way it
occurs to me that
um you know this this binary distinction
between uh there are agents some of them
like me some of them different maybe
competitors whatever but there are there
are some agents that i can communicate
with or can i receive influence or
signals from and then and then there's
this environment which is you know
something that we assume or i mean some
some cultures of course don't assume
that but but we can assume that it has
very low or zero agency meaning that it
just is this sort of dumb un purposeless
universe and it's on us to sort of
figure out what it's doing right so it
occurs to me that that that distinction
maybe shouldn't be binary and maybe what
we want to be thinking about is as an
agent when you are
receiving something uh from from what
you think is the outside you might want
to estimate uh
what is the agency on the other end and
you might want to do this for the
following reason right and i started
thinking about this by imagining what it
would be like to be in an internal
partition or a chunk of a giant neural
net being trained you know you you live
if if that's you you live in a very
mindful universe you know you could
catch on to the fact that you know what
i'm being i'm being trained for
something you know the world like there
are bigger patterns here and of course
it moves in inscrutable ways and
everything because i can't you know i
can't sort of
i can't understand the whole pattern of
what's going on but i can definitely
tell that it's rewarding me and
punishing me for specific behaviors
right and of course some people do feel
that way about the universe and at large
that there are patterns that
that are not just you know not quote
unquote just physics and so
so the reason the reason i i think and
this extends to you know we have
supervised learning and unsupervised
learning and again we think of those as
kind of binary things right is there
some sort of intelligence on the other
end telling you what's right and wrong
or is it just on you to abstract
patterns from the environment and the
reason i think we this matters is that
if if uh if if you are
uh trying to learn from the environment
meaning there's only one agent involved
there's right there's that's you there's
one agent and then there's this sort of
unthinking universe around you then you
are pretty much guaranteed that whatever
uh whatever you can manage to infer to
it will be to your utility it's on you
to figure out you to learn whatever you
can
if there's another agent on the other
side and you're being trained right
then uh what are the odds that that
agent has your best interests at heart i
mean maybe but maybe not and so if this
is some sort of supervised learning
you have to ask yourself
what is it that i'm being trained and is
it really what i what i want right
there's another there's kind of a whole
thing
that you can imagine evolutionarily that
maybe to avoid uh being hijacked by um
by by by parasites by by you know
competitors by whoever you don't really
want to be trainable too much you you
want to learn but you don't really want
to be trained and so maybe
the idea then is that uh what if what if
and this is okay this is where you know
i really haven't even
talked to anybody about this yet so this
is again could be a very amateuric stuff
but but what if uh something like back
propagation or whatever what if that
literally hurts what if as a as a right
as an early creature having some sort of
error function forced back through your
channels as opposed to whatever you were
trying to generate yourself what if
that's evolutionarily designed to be
unpleasant and what if uh what you're
trying to do is avoid that happening you
don't want to be trained you want to
learn on your own terms
and you could sort of imagine the
different layers of a feed-forward
artificial neural network where the like
the initial input layer
that
sort of creature gets to see the world
quote-unquote as it is it gets the raw
inputs the next layer and certainly the
layers past that you know the ones on
the right that are abstracting they're
getting all kinds of propaganda filtered
to them by the early layers you know
they don't get to see the real inputs
they get to see whatever the pre of the
prior layers think they should be seeing
and and so maybe if you don't have a
flat network like this but maybe what
you have is a
you know more biologically you have a
kind of a nested um
uh multi-scale kind of system maybe
there's some sort of uh
incentive for the middle layers to try
to sort of crawl leftward so that they
have more raw access to the real world
and not be trapped uh being being fed by
these other agents right so again you
know this is all very qualitative stuff
but you get the idea that's that's kind
of what uh what what what i was thinking
about
nice
dean and then daniel
mike if you want to chat about this this
is what i was doing for about 10 years
unleashing and getting out of the lab
and
getting past the toy model so perhaps we
should
chat about this for a bit can i just
a couple of things
uh chris first of all thank you
for uh i feel like i've come away with a
munich stein volume worth of of coolness
for the last two weeks just listening to
you explain these really well
complicated things to me
uh in ways that i can actually
understand
um
one of the things that i'm i'm still
kind of curious about is
once we let things out of the lab and we
keep them in that variability retained
space
and we're and we don't want to be in
conflict with sort of the basic rules of
of
what quantitative information tells us i
want to kind of go back for one second
what stephen was
kind of closing the 40.1 with and that
is what do we do when we look at things
in in that sort of relational realm that
a lot of
um
indulge indigenous cultures
sort of take up and try to find
themselves
within and
i'm kind of leading to this idea that
there's there's a sort of a subject
matter generalist
that leads to a prediction matter expert
down the road and i i talked to carl i
have it was my question to carl back in
june when he was
talking to us in the active inference
lab and so without getting into any kind
of conflict with the quantum
aspects of this
um what what what do we take out with
with us when we go on a bike ride with
with chris fields
that's that's quantum related that isn't
in conflict with everything we've talked
about today but gives us a better
confidence around the things that we
might encounter and predict
what do you take on your bike chris
yeah what's in your quiver
yeah good question uh
no
once again these these theoretical
frameworks
are languages
and
they
their role is to shape our concepts or
their they are ways of shaping our
concepts
and
um
i think the the fundamental
kind of lesson of
quantum theory for us
is to
not take the boundaries we see
as
literally as we're encouraged to do in
the classical worldview i'll try to
distinguish the classical worldview from
classical physics
because
classical physics by itself
uh again going back to someone like
laplace
um
is
a physics of of
atoms
which are which are you know
sort of elemental
uh
it's not a physics of bounded
macroscopic objects the boundaries even
in classical physics are sort of
arbitrary
and i i think that's what quantum
theory is trying to tell us to
is trying to tell us that these these
are boundaries that we draw
on our blankets
and i think this is in a sense what
uh thinking about the fep is trying to
tell us that
that we have to take this notion that
we're
blanketed entities seriously
when we think about what we're
interacting with
which is
you know everything but us
daniel
in our
closing minutes um if we could just each
give a thought this is really just a
special
and very
powerful uh conversation uh mike with a
back propaganda
amazing thought experiment there
um
and uh no boundary and quantum questions
touching on the work of like ken wilbur
and i think it's just so powerful about
um
does someone have the whole world in
their hands is that a good person is it
a bad person or thing what kind of thing
is that who's on the other side of this
video call
who's on the other side of that other
side
what's the bigger
picture
and it really brings it home that
no it's not just about electrons
this is something that is
across scales and systems so
really just wanted to appreciate the
paper and hope that we continue on this
line of development
and i'll pass it to stephen
uh thanks daniel
yeah i was going to tie this a little
bit some of the threads with
this challenge of having this false
sense of certainty in our culture and
it does feel uncomfortable to be
trained
um
but we do it in the west because we're
confident that we've
got this expert knowledge but then we
suddenly find out we don't know as much
as we do know or we think we know
so that may be why bottom up sort of
organic
indigenous
kind of ways of being or ways of sensing
can feel more holistic so i think there
might be something quite
powerful in that so i like that thread i
think that ties together with um
the challenges
in practice when we try to train up
communities especially if we're working
say if i've worked in rural africa
and communities there that if they don't
feel connected to the
colonizing
narrative
it feels very oppressive so there's
you know there's a lot of good points
there around
where is there coherence where there's
decoherence and also where's their
certainty
and where there's uncertainty so thanks
this is really helpful and
i'll pass it over to blue
well
i've said enough i think i'd like to
hear from mike or carl or chris about
where where you're going or what you're
taking away or or what what are your
final thoughts about the discussion
we've had over the last couple of weeks
i mean i guess i guess the only thing
i'll say is that uh to to me i i really
like um
this idea that it it turns on its head
this this notion that that you have this
this this massive amount of uh mindless
stuff and then somehow you know a little
bit of mind shows up at the end that
that kind of turns it upside down and
and if that's the case then it becomes
then the scaling problem is is really
really interesting right is how how you
scale you know how how biology manages
to scale these things so that they
become synergist synergistic and bigger
and bigger as opposed to you know just
merely a bigger pile of rocks than the
previous pile of rocks and so
that uh right so so those those
mechanisms and in particular in biology
and and so you know i look at it from
from cells getting together to be
organisms and solving problems in the
anatomical space but but i think there
we actually have uh some pretty good
um alternative although very very very
similar in many ways isomorphic but
alternative stories to what happens in
neuroscience to try to understand how
that scaling actually works so i'm super
i'm just super super excited about that
and also the role of the observer and
all of this and the idea that all of
this is based on various observers
observing each other and i think that
makes it it makes for a lot of progress
and and fewer pseudo problems when you
when you look at it that way
carl or chris any final thoughts
well i'll i'll just thank you guys again
for putting this together i thought this
was a fascinating conversation
and
uh
you know if i'll
could throw one more thing into it i i i
think conversations like this are
are evidence
for
uh
the kind of
disciplinary siloization that's been
forced onto us by academic tradition
being an artifact and not
necessarily being all that useful
thanks so much
carl we're going to leave you with the
final word
oh good well
it has to be a thank you doesn't it um
but
you lot for putting this together and
and for the brilliant uh
didactic and also challenging uh
directed uh unpacking of some really um
challenging but i think revealing issues
and also the brilliant questions um my
final word will be future pointing i'm
just taking off um taking up the sleeves
of chris's you know that having unsiloed
conversations is useful just think
thinking about mike having the balls to
come up with his brand new hypothesis
that's two years old so two days of my
apologies
so i thought it was really interesting
i'm just a nice
example of putting things into this kind
of discussion which we're all gonna go
and think about so my immediate thought
was um how on earth does the second
layer in a variational auto encoder or
something doing backprop
act
um and of course it can act if if it's a
recurrent neural network and it can
select which of the um the lowest level
neurons or hidden there sorry not the
non-hidden layer um
units uh to listen to um and of course
we come back again exactly to attention
and selecting those sources of precise
information and where you've got a kind
of internal action so
an interesting and silly thought but
just a nice example of how talking
together can excite interesting and
potentially useful or possibly silly
silly thoughts but again thank you
wonderful i had a great time observing
all of you um and hope to get to do more
of it in the future
yep we can have a dot three anytime
consider
40 um
in the uh
inter measurement interval
while our igus is
digesting
and uh talk to you all soon thanks again
thanks very much everyone thank you bye
bye it's great
you